<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Statistics Homework</title>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://localhost:4000/"/>
 <updated>2025-10-12T11:05:34+02:00</updated>
 <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
 <author>
   <name>Alessandro Maone - 1945149</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Homework 2 - Analysis of Security Incident Distributions</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/homework2/"/>
   <updated>2025-10-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/homework2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this homework, I analyze a dataset of security incidents focusing on three key metrics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incident Duration (minutes)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data Leaked (MB)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detection Time (hours)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These metrics are crucial for understanding patterns in security breaches and improving response strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;methodology&quot;&gt;Methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;data-generation-and-storage&quot;&gt;Data Generation and Storage&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a realistic dataset, I implemented a Python-based data generation system that produces security incident data following specific statistical distributions. The data was stored in a PostgreSQL database using the following approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Database Setup&lt;/strong&gt;: Created a PostgreSQL table &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;security_incidents&lt;/code&gt; with columns for incident duration, data leaked, and detection time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Generation&lt;/strong&gt;: Used NumPy to generate statistically realistic data:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Normal distribution for incident durations&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Log-normal distribution for data leaks&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Exponential distribution for detection times&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Storage&lt;/strong&gt;: Utilized SQLAlchemy to efficiently store the generated data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;visualization&quot;&gt;Visualization&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The distributions were visualized using Python’s Matplotlib and Seaborn libraries, creating histograms with kernel density estimation (KDE) curves to better understand the data patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dataset-description-and-analysis&quot;&gt;Dataset Description and Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dataset consists of 31 security incidents, each following specific statistical distributions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-incident-duration-normal-distribution&quot;&gt;1. Incident Duration (Normal Distribution)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/incident_duration.png&quot; alt=&quot;Incident Duration Distribution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The incident duration data shows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mean duration: 64.32 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standard deviation: 15.29 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Range: 37 to 99 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Median (50th percentile): 64 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The distribution appears approximately normal, clustering around the one-hour mark, which aligns with typical security incident patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-data-leaked-log-normal-distribution&quot;&gt;2. Data Leaked (Log-normal Distribution)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/data_leaked.png&quot; alt=&quot;Data Leaked Distribution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data leaked measurements reveal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mean: 3.81 MB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standard deviation: 4.53 MB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Range: 0.22 to 20.08 MB&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Median: 2.34 MB&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right-skewed distribution indicates that while most breaches involve smaller amounts of data, there are occasional large-scale data leaks, which is typical in real-world scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-detection-time-exponential-distribution&quot;&gt;3. Detection Time (Exponential Distribution)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/images/detection_time.png&quot; alt=&quot;Detection Time Distribution&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detection time statistics show:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mean: 1.26 hours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Standard deviation: 1.81 hours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Range: 0.10 to 8.38 hours&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Median: 0.67 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exponential pattern indicates that most incidents are detected relatively quickly, but some take significantly longer, which is consistent with real-world cybersecurity scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;statistical-insights&quot;&gt;Statistical Insights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quartile analysis reveals important operational insights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75% of incidents are resolved within 75.5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75% of data breaches involve less than 4.7 MB of data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;75% of incidents are detected within 1.07 hours&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These metrics provide valuable benchmarks for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setting response time objectives&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Allocating security resources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing incident response strategies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The statistical analysis reveals patterns that can inform cybersecurity strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incident durations follow a predictable pattern, useful for resource planning&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data leaks show a long-tail distribution, highlighting the need for scalable response capabilities&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Detection times demonstrate the importance of early warning systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These insights can help organizations better prepare for and respond to security incidents, particularly in allocating resources and setting response time targets.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Homework 1 - What’s is statistics, and why can it be useful for cybersecurity?</title>
   <link href="http://localhost:4000/homework1/"/>
   <updated>2025-10-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://localhost:4000/homework1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we begin our journey into the intersection of statistics and cybersecurity, it’s essential to understand why these two disciplines are increasingly intertwined. In an era where cyber threats evolve daily and the cost of data breaches continues to climb, statistical methods have become indispensable tools in the cybersecurity arsenal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-statistics&quot;&gt;What is Statistics?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics is the science of collecting, analyzing, interpreting, and presenting data. It provides systematic methods for understanding patterns, making predictions, and drawing conclusions from information—even when that information is incomplete or uncertain. At its core, statistics helps us answer questions like: What is normal? What is unusual? What patterns exist in the data? And crucially for cybersecurity: What behaviors indicate a potential threat?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-growing-importance-of-statistics-in-cybersecurity&quot;&gt;The Growing Importance of Statistics in Cybersecurity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cybersecurity landscape in 2024-2025 highlights why statistical approaches are more critical than ever. Recent data shows that the global average cost of a data breach reached $4.88 million in 2024, representing a 10% increase from the previous year&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;. Organizations now take an average of 277 days to identify and contain a data breach, with credential-related breaches requiring even longer—up to 328 days&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These sobering statistics underscore a fundamental challenge: threats are becoming more sophisticated, more frequent, and more costly. With approximately 4,000 cyber attacks occurring daily worldwide&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;, the sheer volume of security events makes manual analysis impossible. This is precisely where statistical methods become invaluable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;key-applications-of-statistics-in-cybersecurity&quot;&gt;Key Applications of Statistics in Cybersecurity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-anomaly-detection&quot;&gt;1. Anomaly Detection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most powerful applications of statistics in cybersecurity is anomaly detection—the ability to identify unusual patterns that deviate from normal behavior. Statistical approaches like outlier detection use measures such as mean, variance, and standard deviation to establish baselines of “normal” network activity or user behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When systems observe deviations from these established norms, they can flag potential security incidents. For example, if a user account suddenly accesses an unusual volume of files at 3 AM, statistical models can recognize this as anomalous behavior worthy of investigation. These techniques range from classical statistical methods to more advanced machine learning models that can adapt to changing patterns over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-intrusion-detection-systems&quot;&gt;2. Intrusion Detection Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intrusion Detection Systems (IDS) heavily rely on statistical techniques to distinguish between legitimate traffic and potential attacks. These systems build behavioral and knowledge profiles based on historical data, using statistical analysis to classify activities as normal or suspicious. Both supervised and unsupervised statistical learning methods help these systems become more accurate over time, reducing false positives while catching genuine threats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-risk-assessment-and-prediction&quot;&gt;3. Risk Assessment and Prediction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics enables cybersecurity professionals to move from reactive to proactive security postures. By analyzing historical attack data, vulnerability assessments, and threat intelligence, statistical models can predict where vulnerabilities are most likely to be exploited and which assets face the highest risk. This allows organizations to allocate security resources more effectively and prioritize remediation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-pattern-recognition-and-threat-intelligence&quot;&gt;4. Pattern Recognition and Threat Intelligence&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical pattern recognition helps identify emerging attack vectors and threat trends. For instance, analysis reveals that over 75% of targeted cyberattacks begin with email phishing campaigns&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;. By applying statistical methods to large datasets of threat indicators, security teams can recognize patterns that signal coordinated attacks, identify malware families, and track threat actor behaviors across different campaigns&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;5-performance-measurement&quot;&gt;5. Performance Measurement&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics also plays a crucial role in measuring the effectiveness of security controls. Metrics such as mean time to detect (MTTD), mean time to respond (MTTR), false positive rates, and detection accuracy all rely on statistical analysis. These measurements help organizations understand whether their security investments are working and where improvements are needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-human-element&quot;&gt;The Human Element&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, statistics also helps us understand the human factors in cybersecurity. Data shows that 70% of organizations have users being served malware ads through their browsers&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;, and that proper education can significantly reduce successful phishing attempts. Multi-factor authentication, for example, prevents 99.9% of phishing attacks&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;—a statistically significant improvement that highlights the value of combining technical and educational approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;looking-forward&quot;&gt;Looking Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As cyber threats continue to evolve, particularly with the emergence of AI-powered attacks, statistical methods will become even more critical. The field is moving toward more sophisticated applications, including predictive analytics, behavioral biometrics, and adaptive security systems that learn and improve over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The integration of statistics with machine learning and artificial intelligence represents the future of cybersecurity defense. However, the fundamental statistical principles—understanding distributions, identifying outliers, testing hypotheses, and quantifying uncertainty—remain at the heart of all these advanced applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistics is far more than just numbers and graphs in cybersecurity—it’s the foundation for making data-driven security decisions in an environment characterized by uncertainty and rapidly evolving threats. As we progress through this course, we’ll explore how these statistical methods are applied in practice, gaining the analytical skills needed to protect systems and data in an increasingly connected world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The marriage of statistics and cybersecurity isn’t just useful—it’s essential. In a domain where threats can materialize in microseconds and the cost of failure is measured in millions, statistical methods provide the clarity, predictive power, and systematic approach needed to stay ahead of adversaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;IBM Security. (2024). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/security/data-breach&quot;&gt;Cost of a Data Breach Report 2024&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Kure, H. I., Islam, S., &amp;amp; Razzaque, M. A. (2019). &lt;a href=&quot;https://cybersecurity.springeropen.com/articles/10.1186/s42400-019-0038-7&quot;&gt;Survey of intrusion detection systems: techniques, datasets and challenges&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Cybersecurity&lt;/em&gt;, 2(1).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;XenonStack. (2024). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.xenonstack.com/insights/cyber-network-security&quot;&gt;Quick Guide for Anomaly Detection in Cybersecurity Networks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Exabeam. (2025). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.exabeam.com/explainers/ueba/behavior-anomaly-detection-techniques-and-best-practices/&quot;&gt;Behavior Anomaly Detection: Techniques and Best Practices&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;SentinelOne. (2025). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sentinelone.com/cybersecurity-101/cybersecurity/cyber-security-statistics/&quot;&gt;Key Cyber Security Statistics for 2025&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fortinet. (2025). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fortinet.com/resources/cyberglossary/cybersecurity-statistics&quot;&gt;Top Cybersecurity Statistics: Facts, Stats and Breaches for 2025&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
